Guide to the Ballet West promotional materials audio-visual collection 1976-1987
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Ballet West promotional materials audio-visual collection
1976-1987
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0322
Ballet West (U.S.)
41 reel-to-reel audiotapes, 9 audiocassettes, and 1 16mm film
The Ballet West promotional materials audio-visual collection (1976-1987) consists almost entirely of audio recordings of radio advertisements for Ballet West tickets and productions. There are also audio recordins of Ballet West personalities on the "State of the Arts" radio program one television advertisment recorded on 16mm film. A professional ballet company, Ballet West was established in 1963 and offers a season of performances at the Salt Lake City, Utah's Capitol Theatre.
Organizational History
Ballet West is a professional ballet company founded in 1963 by Utah's "First Lady of the Arts" Glenn Walker Wallace and Willam F. Christensen, founder of the University of Utah's ballet department and Ballet West's first artistic director. The company has subsequently been led by artistic directors Bruce Marks, John Hart, Jonas Kåge and Adam Sklute. In addition to its annual season of performances at the Capitol Theatre in downtown Salt Lake City, Utah, Ballet West has toured the world several times with its classical ballet performances.
The Ballet West promotional materials audio-visual collection (1976-1987) consists almost entirely of audio recordings of radio advertisements for Ballet West tickets and productions. There are also audio recordins of Ballet West personalities on the "State of the Arts" radio program one television advertisment recorded on 16mm film.
The materials are arranged rougly chronologically by format.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Ballet Archives audio-visual collection (A0247), the Ballet West records (Accn 1129) and the Ballet Archives photograph collection (P0247).
Dance--Utah-History--Sources; Dance companies--Utah-History--Sources; Performing Arts; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; Moving images; Sound recordings
- "Don Juan" radio promotion, 1976 January 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 1)
- "Cinderella" radio promotions, 1976 March 23; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 2)
- Season ticket radio promotion, 1976 April 22; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 3)
- "Nutcracker" radio promotion, 1976; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 4)
- Ticket radio promotion, 1977-1978; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 5)
- Telebash radio promotion, 1977; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 6)
- "The Discover Season" radio promotions, 1977; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 7)
- Ticket radio promotion, 1977-78; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 8)
- "Don Quixote" radio promotions, 1977; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 9)
- "Giselle" radio promotion, 1977; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 10)
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotions, 1977; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 11)
- "Swan Lake Last Bow" radio promotions, 1978 March 09; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 12-13)
- Radio promotions, 1982; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 14)
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotions, 1982; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 15)
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotion (extended), 1984; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 16-17)
  Nutcracker doll and bear presentation. Ten minutes.
  2 copies
- "Invitation to Dance" radio promotion, 1984 March 16; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 18)
- "Don Quixote" radio promotions, 1984 August 27; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 19)
  Radio spots entitled "Don Quixote Coming" and "Don Quixote Here."
- "Petrouchka" television audio promotion, 1985 September 30; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 20)
- 1985-1986 season radio promotions, 1985 June; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 21-22)
- "Sleeping Beauty" radio promotion, 1986 January 14; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 23)
- "A Salute to Ballanchine" radio promotion, 1986 March 18; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 24)
- 1986-1987 season radio promotions, Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 25-26)
- "Gershwin" radio promotion, 1987 March 5; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 27)
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotions, 1987 October 30; 1987 November 30; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 28-29)
- KSL radio and television audio promotions, 1987; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 30)
- Unidentified radio promotions, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 31)
- "A Celebration of the American Experience" radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 32)
- "Romeo and Juliet" radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 33)
- Unidentified radio promotions, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 34)
- "Sleeping Beauty" radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 35)
- Unidentified radio promotions, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 36)
- Touring radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 37)
- Fundraising radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 38)
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 39)
- Telebash radio promotion, 1979 October 02; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 40)
- Glittering Gala radio promotion, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 41)
- There is no item 42. (Item 42)
- Denver Symphony radio promotions, 1980 December-1981 January; Audiocassette (Cassette 43)
  1 Promotion for Ballet West's appearance with the Denver Symphony, in Denver, Colorado in January, 1981.
  2 Promotion for the Denver Symphony's performance of Handel's "Messiah" in December, 1980
- "The Nutcracker" radio promotions, 1982; Audiocassette (Cassette 44)
  1 Two promotions for performances of "The Nutcracker" in Salt Lake City.
  2 Various promotions not related to Ballet West.
- "Swan Lake" wiht the Denver Symphony radio promotion, 1982 April 14; Audiocassette (Cassette 45)
- "Sleeping Beauty" radio promotions, 1986 February; Audiocassette (Cassette 46)
- "State of the Arts" radio program, 1986; Audiocassette (Cassette 47)
  Broadcast on KWHO, Salt Lake City.
  The guest is Sondra Sugai, Associate Artistic Director of Ballet West, who discusses the company's 20th anniversary. Other topics include motivating performers; the stages of a dancer's growth; audience recognition of the company's improvement; artistic milestones in the company's history; Bruce Marks; works of the new choreographer (Helen Douglass); Sugai's reasons for her devotion to dance; performing Songs of the Ballet, Mistress of Sorrow and Ballanchine's Stars and Stripes; Helen Douglass and Rite of Spring; performing Etudes; Bruce Marks and Pipe Dreams; the performing of Beauty and the Beast; and the formulation of a successful season. 28 minutes.
- "State of the Arts" radio program, 1983 October; Audiocassette (Cassette 48)
  On side A the guest is Helen Douglass, Resident Choreographer of Ballet West. Douglass discusses her past as a dancer; chore-ography; the Boston Choreographer's Competition; her initial experiences as a choreographer; developing origi-nality; working on Rite of Spring; the pros and cons of her position as Resident Choreographer. 33 minutes.
  On side B the guests are Stacy Swaner and Bruce Caldwell, Principal Dancers at Ballet West. Caldwell and Swaner discuss their early training as dancers; dedication to dance; daily regimen; the effect of injuries; greatest fears as dancers; strengths and weaknesses; favorite roles; and future after dance. 35 minutes.
- "State of the Arts" radio program, 1983; Audiocassette (Cassette 49)
  On side A the guest is Willam Christensen, founder of Ballet West. Background information on Christensen and Ballet West is included. Topics of discussion are Christensen's experiences at the University of Utah; the sources of his "vision;" early fundraising; the importance of touring; early performances; Cinderella; his hopes for Ballet West; guest artists; Bruce Marks as new Artistic Director; the ballet academy; and the dance careers of former Utahns. 40 minutes.
  On side B the guest is Bruce Marks, Artistic Director of Ballet West. The opening remarks of this segment are not recorded. Topics of discussion include Marks' experiences and classmates at the High School of the Performing Arts in New York City; his reasons for becoming a dancer; performing as a soloist in Lucia di Lammermoor at the Metropolitan Opera; his experiences as a dancer at, and touring with, the American Ballet Theater; his self-description as a dancer; memorable performances; his reasons for giving up performing; the critical acclaim of Ballet West; choreographing; his opinion of holding an administrative position; and the ballet school. 28 minutes.
- "KRP Night at the Ballet" radio promotion, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 50)
  1 One promotion for "KRP Night at the Ballet" in Salt Lake City (a performance of "Anna Karenina").
  2 News coverage unrelated to Ballet West. Three minutes.
- Season ticket radio promotion, undated; Audiocassette (Cassette 51)
- "Ballet?", circa 1980; 16mm film Sound, color (Othertype 52)
  One television promotion for Ballet West made by Harris and Love Film. One minute.